<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A declaration made by King James, in Scotland; concerning, church-government, and presbyters.</title>
            <title>Declaratioun of the Kings Majesties intentioun and meaning toward the lait actis of Parliament. English and Scots.</title>
            <author>Adamson, Patrick, 1537-1592.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1646</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 33 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 7 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A87463</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing J132</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E506_27</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R202599</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99862827</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99862827</idno>
            <idno type="VID">115004</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A87463)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 115004)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 80:E506[27])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A declaration made by King James, in Scotland; concerning, church-government, and presbyters.</title>
                  <title>Declaratioun of the Kings Majesties intentioun and meaning toward the lait actis of Parliament. English and Scots.</title>
                  <author>Adamson, Patrick, 1537-1592.</author>
                  <author>James I, King of England, 1566-1625.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 22 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Now printed, in English and Scotch; for Matthew Walbancke, at Grays-Inne gate,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London] :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1646.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Written by Patrick Adamson for James I.</note>
                  <note>Originally published in Scots in 1585 as: A declaratioun of the Kings Majesties intentioun and meaning toward the lait actis of Parliament.</note>
                  <note>"A declaratioun of the Kings Majesties intentioun and meaning toward the lait actis of Parliament", the original Scots text, has separate title page with arms of Charles I and imprint "Imprinted at Edinburgh, by Thomas Vautroullier. 1585."; pagination and register are continuous.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "Aprill 6th".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Scotland --  Church history --  16th century --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Scotland --  History --  James VI, 1567-1625 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-12</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-01</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-11</date>
            <label>Leah Yurasek</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-11</date>
            <label>Leah Yurasek</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:115004:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A DECLARATION MADE BY King James, IN SCOTLAND; CONCERNING, <hi>Church-Government, and</hi> PRESBYTERS.</p>
            <figure>
               <figDesc>royal blazon or coat of arms</figDesc>
               <head>C R</head>
               <q>HONI SOIT QVI MAL Y PENSE</q>
               <q>DIEV ET MON DROIT</q>
            </figure>
            <p>Now Printed, in Engliſh and Scotch; for <hi>Matthew Walbancke,</hi> at <hi>Grayſ-Inne</hi> Gate. 1646.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:115004:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:115004:2"/>
            <head>A Declaration of King <hi>James,</hi> made in <hi>Scotland, Anno Dom. 1585.</hi> Concerning Church-Government.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">F</seg>Or ſo much as here are ſome evill affected men, that go about (ſo farre as lyeth in them) to invent lyes and ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lumnies to ſtain and impair the Kings Majeſties fame and honour, and raiſe brutes as if his Majeſtie had declined to Papiſtry, and had made many Acts to derogate the free paſſage of the Goſpell, good order and diſcipline in the Church, which brutes are nouriſht and entertained by rebellious ſubjects, who would gladly cover their ſeditious enterpriſes under pretext of religion, albeit there can be no religion in ſuch as raiſe armour and diſquiet the eſtate of their native Soveraign, and perjuriouſly have contraried the Oath bond and obligation of their faith, whereunto they have ſworn and ſubſcribed. Therefore that His Majeſties faithfull Subjects be not abuſed with ſuch ſlanderous reports, and His highneſſe good and affectio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate friends in other Countries may underſtand the verity of his upright inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, His Majeſty hath commanded this brief declaration of certain of His Majeſties Acts of Parliament held in <hi>May</hi> 1584. to be publiſht and imprinted, to the effect, that the indirect practices of ſuch as ſlander His Majeſty and his lawes, may be detected and diſcovered.</p>
            <p>IN the firſt Act, His Majeſtie ratifieth and approveth the true profeſſion of the Goſpell, ſincere preaching of the word, and adminiſtration of the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>craments, preſently by the goodneſſe of God eſtabliſhed in this Realm; and alloweth of the confeſſion of the faith ſet down by Act of Parliament the firſt year of His Majeſties reign: Like as His Highneſſe not onely profeſſeth the ſame in all ſincerity, but (praiſed be God) is come to that maturity of judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:115004:3"/>by reading and hearing the Word of God, that His highneſſe is able to convince, and overthrow by the doctrine of the Prophets and Apoſtles, the moſt learned of the contrary ſect of the Adverſaries: So as <hi>Plato</hi> affirms that Commonwealth to be moſt happy wherein a Philoſopher reigneth, or he that reigneth is a Philoſopher: we may much more eſteem this Country of <hi>Scot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> to be fortunate, wherein our King is a Theologue, and his heart repleniſht with the knowledge of the heavenly philoſophy, for the comfort not only of his good ſubjects and friends in other countries, but of them that profeſſe the Goſpell every where, he being a King of great expectation, to whom his birth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>right hath not only deſtinate and provided great Kingdomes, but much more <hi>His Majeſties</hi> vertue, godlineſſe and learning, and daily encreaſe of all hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly ſciences, do promiſe and aſſure him of the mighty protection of God, and favour of all them that fear his holy name.</p>
            <p>IN the ſecond Act, his <hi>Maj.</hi> royall authority over all eſtates both ſpirituall and temporall is confirmed, which act ſome of malice and others of ignorance, do traduce, as if his <hi>Maj.</hi> pretended to be head of the Church, a name which His Maj. acknowledgeth to be proper and peculiar to the Son of God the Saviour of the world, who is the head, and beſtoweth life ſpirituall upon the members of his myſticall body, and he having received the holy ſpirit in all abundance ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth every one of the faithfull partakers, according to the meaſure of faith be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtowed upon them, of the which number of the head Chriſt <hi>His Maj.</hi> acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledgeth himſelf to be a member, baptized in his name, partaker of the myſtery of the croſſe and holy communion, and attending with the faithfull for the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming of the Lord, and the finall reſtitution of Gods elect. And notwithſtanding his <hi>Maj.</hi> ſurely underſtands by the ſcriptures, that he is the principall member appointed by the law of God, to ſee God glorified, vice puniſht, and vertue maintain'd within his realm, and the ſoveraign judgment for a godly quietneſſe and order in the common-wealth, to appertain to His highneſſe care and ſolici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude: which power of his highneſſe certain miniſters (being called before His <hi>Maj.</hi> for ſeditious and factious ſermons, and ſtirring up the people to rebell a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt their native King) would in no wiſe acknowledg, but diſclaimed His au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority as an incompetent Judge; and eſpecially one Mr. <hi>Andrew Melvile,</hi> an am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitious perſon, of a ſalt and fiery humour, uſurping the Pulpit of <hi>Sandrois,</hi> with out any lawfull calling, and privy at that time to certain conſpiracies againſt <hi>His Maj.</hi> went about in his ſermon upon a Sunday, to inflame the hearts of the people, by odious compariſons of His <hi>Maj.</hi> progenitors and councell. Albeit the duty of a faithfull preacher of the Goſpel, be rather to exhort the people to the obedience of their native King, nor by popular ſermons, which hath been the decay of great commonwealths, and hath greatly in times paſt diſquieted this E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtate. The ſaid <hi>Mr. Andrew</hi> called before His highneſſe anſwered, he would not be judg'd by the King and his Councell, becauſe he ſpake the ſame in a Pulpit, which Pulpit (in effect) he alledged to be exempt from the judgment and cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:115004:3"/>of Princes, as if that holy place ſanctified to the word of God, might be a colour to any ſedition againſt lawfull authority without puniſhment: His <hi>Maj.</hi> (being a moſt gracious Prince) was unwilling to uſe rigour againſt the ſaid Mr. <hi>Andrew,</hi> if he had humbly ſubmitted himſelf, acknowledg'd his offence and craved pardon; but he (afraid of his own guiltineſſe, being private to divers conſpiracies before, fled into England; whoſe naughty and preſumptuous refu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing of his Highneſſe judgment, was the occaſion of the making of the 2d. Act; That none ſhould decline his Highneſſe Authority, in reſpect that the common proverb is, that <hi>Ex malis moribus bonae leges natae ſunt:</hi> that is, Of evill manners good Laws proceed; And indeed intollerable arrogancy in any Subject called before his Prince, profeſſing and authorizing the ſame truth to diſclaim his au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority; neither do the Prophets, Apoſtles, or others, conducted by the Spirit of God miniſter the like example: For it is a great errour to affirme (as many do) that Princes and Magiſtrates have only power to take order in civill affaires, and that Eccleſiaſticall matters do onely belong to the Miniſtry; by which means the Pope of <hi>Rome</hi> hath exempt Himſelf and His Clergie from all judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of Princes, and hath made himſelf to be Judge of Judges, and to be judged of no man: whereas by the contrary, not onely by the examples of the Godly Governours, Judges, and Kings, of the antient Teſtament; but alſo by the new Teſtament, and the who<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e Hiſtory of the Primitive Church,; in the which, the Emperours judged over the Biſhops of <hi>Rome,</hi> depoſed them from their Seates, appointed Judges to acknowledg and decide in Cauſes Eccleſiaſticall, vindicate innocent men as <hi>Athanaſius</hi> from the determination of the Councell holden at <hi>Tyrus,</hi> and by infinite good reaſons, which ſhall be ſet down (by the grace of God) in a ſeverall Work, ſhall be ſufficiently proved: But this appeareth at this preſent to be an unprofitable queſtion, which hath no ground upon their part, but of the prepoſterous imitation of the pretended juriſdiction of the Pope of <hi>Rome;</hi> For if there were any queſtion in this Land of Hereſie, wherby the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>found Miſteries of the Scriptures behoved to be ſearched out, His Maj. would uſe the ſame remedy (as moſt expedient) which the moſt godly Emperors have uſed, and his Maj. following their example, would convene the Councel of lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned Paſtours, that by conference of Scriptures the Truth might be opened, and Hereſie repreſſed. But (praiſed be God) we have no ſuch controverſies in this Land, nor hath Hereſie taken any deeproot in the Country; but certain of the Miniſtry joyning themſelvs to Rebels have travelled to diſquiet the eſtate with ſuch queſtions, that the People might enjoy a ſiniſter opinion of his Maj. upright proceedings; Neither is it his Maj. intention to take away the lawfull and or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary judgment in the Church, whereby Diſcipline and good order might de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cay, but rather to preſerve, maintain, &amp; encreaſe the ſame. And as there is in the Realm Juſtices, Conſtables, Sheriffes, Provoſts, Bayliffes, and other Judges in Temporall matters; ſo His Majeſty alloweth that all things may bee done in order, and a Godly Harmony may be preſerved in the whole Eſtate.
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:115004:4"/>The Synodall Aſſemblies by the Biſhops, or Commiſſioners (where the place is vacant) to be convened twice in the year, to have the ordinary triall of matters belonging to the Miniſtery and their eſtate, always reſerved to His highneſſe, that if they or any of them do amiſſe, neglect their duty, diſquiet the eſtate, or offend in ſuch manner and ſort, that they in no wiſe pretend that immunity, pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viledge and exemption, which only was invented by the Popes of <hi>Rome,</hi> to tread under foot the Scepters of Princes, and to eſtabliſh an Eccleſiaſticall tyranny within this country, under pretext of new-invented Presbyteries, which nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſhould anſwer to the King, nor Biſhop under His Majeſty, but ſhould have an infinire juriſdiction, as neither Law of God nor man can tollerate; which is onely His Majeſties intention to repreſſe, and not to take away any godly or ſolid order in the Church, as hereafter ſhall appear.</p>
            <p>THe fourth Act of His Majeſties foreſaid Parliament, diſcharges all judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments Eccleſiaſticall, and all aſſemblies which are not allowed by His Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty in Parliament, which Act eſpecially concerneth the removing and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charging of that form late invented in this land called the Presbytery, wherein any number of Miniſters of any certain precinct and bounds accompting them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves all to be equall, without any difference; and gathering unto them certain Gentlemen and others of His Majeſties ſubjects, uſurped all the whole Eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiaſticall juriſdiction, and altered the Lawes at their own appetite, without the knowledge and approbation of the King or the eſtate; a form of doing with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any example of any Nation ſubject to any Chriſtian Prince. The perill whereof did ſo encreaſe, that in caſe in due ſeaſon it had not been repreſſed and forbidden by His Majeſties lawes, the ſame had troubled the whole country, and it being tried by His highneſſe to be the overthrow of His Majeſties eſtate, the decay of His crown, and a ready introduction to Anabaptiſme, and popular confuſion in all eſtates, His Majeſty hath countermanded the ſame. And that the Reader may underſtand the danger thereof by many inconveniences, which thereby enſued in this Land; I will onely ſet down one, whereby ye may un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand what perill was in the reſt. The Embaſſadour of France being to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn home to his own country, the King commanded the Provoſt-Bailifs and councell of <hi>Edinburgh</hi> to give him the banquet, that he might be diſmiſt hono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rably, according to the amity of ancient times betwixt the two Nations; This command was given on Saturday by His highneſſe, and the banquet appointed to be on the Munday: A number of the foreſaid Presbyterie underſtanding thereof, convened themſelves on Sunday in the morning, and preſumptuouſly determin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d and agreed, that the Miniſters of <hi>Edinburgh</hi> ſhould proclaim a Faſt upon the ſaid <hi>Munday,</hi> where their ſeverall Miniſters one after another made three diverſe ſermons, invectives againſt the Provoſt-Bailiffs, and councell for the time, and the Noblemen in the country who aſſiſted the banquet at. His Majeſties command. The foreſaid Presbyterie called and perſued them, and
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:115004:4"/>ſcarcely by His Majeſties authority could be with-holden from excommunica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting the ſaid Magiſtrates and Noblemen, for obeying only His highneſſe lawfull command, which the law of all countries called <hi>jus gentium,</hi> requireth towards Embaſſadors of forraign countries: And not onely in this, but innumerable o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther things, their commandement was oppoſite directly under pain of Excom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munication, to the Kings Majeſty and His laws, which form of doing ingen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred nothing but diſquiet, ſedition and trouble, as may manifeſtly appear, in that the ſpeciall authors of the inventing, promoting &amp; aſſiſting of the aforeſaid pretended Presbyters, have joyned themſelves with His Majeſties Rebels; and flying forth of the Realm in reſpect of their guiltineſſe, have diſcovered what malicious practices were deviſed amongſt them, if God had not in time pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided remedy. The other form of judgment which His Majeſty hath diſchar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged, is the generall aſſembly of the whole Clergy of the Realm, under pretence whereof, a number of Miniſters from ſeverall Presbyteries did aſſemble, with ſome Gentlemen of the country, whereof ſome for that time male-contents of the State, ſought that colour, as favourers of the miniſtery; by which they have practiſed many enterpriſes in the Realm; where there was no certain law in Eccleſiaſticall affairs, but all depended upon the ſaid generall convention, where the laws of the Church were alterable after the plurality of votes, which for the moſt part ſucceeded to the moſt unlearned of the multitude: This ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall aſſembly, amongſt other things, did appoint and agree with His Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſties Regents in His highneſſe minority, that the eſtate of Biſhops (which is one of the eſtates of the Parliament) ſhould be maintained and authorized, as it is regiſtred in the books of councell, and ſubſcribed by the Commiſſioners for the time: which order was obſerved many years, and Biſhops by their conſents appointed to the Dioceſſes, where within this late time in aſſemblies holden at <hi>Dundee</hi> and <hi>Glaſcow</hi> reſpective, the foreſaid Miniſters and aſſemblies, took upon them contrary to their own hand-writing, to diſcharge the eſtate, and to declare the ſame to be unlawfull in their pretended manner: And there commanded the Biſhops of the Country, to lay down and leave their Offices and juriſdictions, and that in no wiſe they ſhould paſſe to the Kings Majeſties Councell or Parliament, without commiſſion obtained from their Aſſembly; That they ſhould vote nothing in Parliament or Councell, but according to their acts and injunctions: And further, they directed their Commiſſioners to the Kings Majeſty, commanding him and the Councell, under the pain of the cenſures of the Church (whereby they underſtood excommunication) to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>point no Biſhop in times to come, becauſe they had concluded that eſtate to be unlawfull. And notwithſtanding that which they would have dejected in the Biſhops, they concluded to erect in themſelves, deſiring that ſuch Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſioners as they ſhould ſend to Parliament and Councell, might be authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zed in place of the eſtate, whereby it ſhould have come to paſſe, that whereas now His Majeſty may ſelect the moſt godly, learned, wiſe, and experimented of
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:115004:5"/>the Miniſtery to be on His Majeſties Eſtate, His highneſſe ſhould have been by that means compelled to accept ſuch as the multitude by an odd vote of the moſt unlearned ſhould have appointed, which could not tend but to the over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throw of the realm, whereof that Eſtate hath been a ſpeciall ſtay: After they had diſcharged Biſhops, they agreed to have Superintendents, Commiſſioners, and Viſitors, but in the end they decreed that there ſhould be no difference a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt the Miniſters, and imagined that new form of Presbytery, whereof we have ſpoken before: Neither was there any other apparance that they ſhould have ſtayed from ſuch daily alterations in the Common-wealth, which could not but continually be diſquieted, where the law of conſcience (which they maintained by the ſword of curſing) was ſubject to ſuch mutations at the arbi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trement of a number, whereof the moſt part had not greatly taſted of learning: After the foreſaid aſſembly was accuſtomed not only to preſcribe the law to the King and State, but alſo did at certain times appoint generall Faſtings tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roughout the realm; eſpecially when ſome factioners in the country were to move any great enterpriſe: For at the Faſt all the Miniſters were commanded by the ſaid aſſembly to ſing one ſong, and to cry out of the abuſes (as they term<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed it) of the Court and State for the time: whereby it is moſt certain, great alte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations have enſued in this land; untill at the good pleaſure of God, and his bleſſing towards His Maj. the pretext of the laſt Faſt was diſcovered, and His highneſſe delivered from ſuch attempts: whereby His Maj. hath been juſtly mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved to diſcharge ſuch conventions, which might import ſo prejudicially to His Eſtate; but eſpecially. His Maj. had no ſmall occaſion. Whereas the ſame aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly being convened at <hi>Edinburgh</hi> the day of did authorize and avow the fact perpetrate at <hi>Ruthuen</hi> in the taking of His highneſſe moſt noble perſon: The which deed; although His Maj. with the advice of His States in Parliament hath counted to be treaſonable, the ſaid aſſembly (eſteeming their judgement to be the ſoveraign judgment of the realm) hath not onely approved the ſame, but ordained all them to be excommunicate who would not ſubſcribe and allow the ſame: So the Acts of this Aſſembly, and the Acts of Eſtate directly in civill matters, with which the Aſſembly ſhould not have medled; it behoved His highneſſe either to diſcharge himſelf of the crown, or the Miniſtery of that form of aſſembly, which in very deed in it ſelf, without the Kings Majeſties licenſe and approbation could not be lawfull. Like as generall Councels at no time could aſſemble but by the command of the Emperor for the time. And our King hath no leſſe power in his own realm, then any of them had in the Empire; yea the Biſhop of St. <hi>Andrews</hi> had not in time of Popery power to convene the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops and Clergy out of his own Dioceſſe, without licenſe impetrate before of His higneſſe moſt noble progenitors of good memory, and the cauſes thereof intimated and allowed: Notwithſtanding that His Maj. intention and meaning may be fully underſtood, it is His highneſſe wil, that the Biſhop or Commiſſio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of any Dioceſſe or Province, or part thereof, ſhall at their Viſitation ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>point
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:115004:5"/>in every pariſh (according to the greatnes thereof) ſome honeſt, vertuous and diſcreet men, to concur and aſſiſt the Miniſter, and to have the overſight and cenſure of the manners and behaviour of the people of that Pariſh: And that there be any notable offence worthy of puniſhment, that the Biſh. and Com. be advertiſed thereof, who ſhall have an Officer of arms to concur with his de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cree for the puniſhment of vice, and execution to follow thereupon; that they who contemn the godly and lawfull Order of the Church, may finde by experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence His Majeſties diſpleaſure, and be puniſht according to their deſervings.</p>
            <p>And further, his Maj. upon neceſſary occaſions which may happen by divers manners of wayes amongſt the Clergy, upon humble ſupplications made to his Highneſſe will not refuſe to grant them licence to convene: to wit, the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops, Commiſſioners, and ſome of the moſt vertuous, learned, godly of their Dioceſſe, where ſuch Eccleſiaſticall matters as appertain to the Uniformity of Doctrine, and conſervation of any godly order in the Church, may be intreated and concluded in his Maj. own preſence, or ſome of his Maj. honourable Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cell, who ſhall aſſiſt for the time; where if neceſſity ſo require a publique Faſt throughout the whole Realm may be decreed, and by his Maj. Authority pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claimed, to avoid the eminent diſpleaſure and danger of the wrath of the Lords judgments, which is the right end of the publike Humiliation, and not under pretext thereof to cover ſuch enterprizes as have heretofore greatly diſquieted and troubled the Peace of this Common-wealth.</p>
            <p>THe XX. Act, ratiſieth, and approveth, and re-eſtabliſheth the eſtate of the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops within the Realm, to have the over-ſight and juriſdiction; every one in their own Dioceſe, which form of government and rule in Eccleſiaſticall af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fairs hath not only continued in the Church from the days of the Apoſtles by continuall ſucceſſion of time, and many Martyrs in that calling ſhed their blood for the Truth; but alſo ſince this Realm embraced and received the Chriſtian Religion, the ſame eſtate hath been maintained to the welfare of the Church, and quietneſſe of the Realm without any interruption while within theſe few yeers, ſome curious and buſie men have practiſed to bring in the Miniſtry an e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quality and purity in all things, aſwell concerning the preaching of the Word, and miniſtration of the Sacraments; as likewiſe in diſcipline, order and policy: The which confuſion his Maj. finding by moſt dangerous experience, to have been the Mother and Nurſe of great factions, ſeditions, and troubles within this Realm, hath with the advice of his Highneſſe Eſtates, maturely, and adviſedly concluded the ſaid pretended party in diſcipline, order, and policy in the Church to be no longer tolerate in this Country, but the ſolicitude and care of my Churches of one Dioceſe, to appertaine to the Biſhop and Commiſſioner thereof, who ſhall be anſwerable to His Majeſty, and Eſtates, for the right ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſtration and diſcharge of the office of particular Miniſters within the bounds of their juriſdiction: For as it becommeth his Majeſty (as <hi>Euſebius</hi> writeth of CONSTANTINE the Great) to be a Biſhop of Biſhops, and
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:115004:6"/>univerſall Biſhop within his realm, in ſo far as His Majeſty ſhould appoint eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry one to diſcharge his duty; ſo His highneſſe cannot (his country being large and great) take him to every Miniſter that ſhall offend and tranſgreſſe againſt duty, or quarrell with the whole number of the miniſtry; but it behoveth His Majeſty to have Biſhops and over-ſeers under him, that may be anſwerable for ſuch bounds, as the law and order of the country hath limited and appointed unto every one of them: And that they having acceſſe unto His Majeſties Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament and Councell, may intercede for the reſt of the brethren of the miniſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, propound their griefs unto His highneſſe and the Eſtates, and receive His Majeſties favourable anſwer therein: The which form doth preſerve a godly harmony, unity, peace and concord in the eſtate, and a ſolid order in the Church. As contrariwiſe the pretended equality divides the ſame, and under pretext of equality, makes ſome of the moſt crafty and ſutable dealers to be advanced and enricht; and in pretending of purity, to ſeek nothing but their own ambition and advancement above the reſt of the ſimple ſort: And notwithſtanding that His Majeſty hath re-eſtabliſht the ſaid eſtate, it is not His highneſſe will and intention, that the fore-ſaid Biſhop ſhall have ſuch full power, as to do within his Dioceſſe what he pleaſeth; For as His Majeſty cannot allow of a popular confuſion, wherein as the proverb witneſſeth, <hi>Nulla tyrannis aquiparanda est tyrannidi multitudinis;</hi> that is, <hi>No tyranny can be compared to the tyranny of a multitude, having power in their hands:</hi> So on the other part, His Majeſties will is, that the Biſhops authority in any grave matter, be limited and circumſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed to 13. of the moſt ancient, wiſe and godly paſtours of his Dioceſſe, ſelected forth of the whole Synodal aſſembly of the Province, by whoſe advice or at the leaſt the moſt part thereof, the grave and weighty affayrs of the Church may be conducted and governed to the glory of God, and quietnes of the realm: Fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, it is His highneſſe will and expreſſe commandement, that their Biſhops and Commiſſioners twice in the year; to wit, ten days after the <hi>Paſche</hi> time, and the ſixt day of September, hold their Synodall aſſemblies of every Dioces, for the keeping good order therein: And if any be refractory or a contemner within their bounds, of the good order of the Church, they may be declared un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to His Majeſty, and puniſht in example of others according to their deſervings. Neither is it His Majeſties meaning or intention, that ſuch Biſhops or Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſioners as ſhall be appointed, ſhall receive their onely and full Commiſſion of His Majeſty, without admiſſion ordinary by ſuch as are appointed to that effect in the Church, but having His highneſſe nomination, preſentation and commendation, as lawfull and only patron, they to be tried and examined that their qualities are ſuch, as they are able and ſufficient to diſcharge their cure and office; and if it ſhall happen any of the ſaid Biſhops or Commiſſioners to be negligent in their Office, or to be ſcandalous or offenſive in their behaviour life and manners in any time comming, it is not His highneſſe will, that they ſhall be exempt from correction, notwithſtanding of any priviledge of His highneſſe
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:115004:6"/>Eſtate, counſell or Parliament, but their labours, travails, diligence, and beha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour, to be tried in the generall aſſembly, not conſiſting of a confuſed multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude, as it was before, but of ſuch worſhipfull perſons as is heretofore preſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed in His highneſſe own preſence, or His <hi>Majeſties</hi> deputies to that effect: Laſt <hi>His Majeſty</hi> giveth Commiſſion to the ſaid Biſhops or Commiſſioners at their viſitations to conſider, in what part of the country the exerciſe or interpreta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Scriptures by conference of a certain number of the miniſtery with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in that bounds may be moſt commodiouſly, in the fifteen days: For as <hi>His Majeſty</hi> inhibits all unlawfull conventions, which may engender troubles and contentions in the Country, ſo <hi>His Majeſty</hi> is well affected to ſee the miniſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry encreaſe in knowledge and underſtanding, and by all means to fortifie and advance the ſame; wherein <hi>His Majeſties</hi> commandement is, that a grave, wiſe, and ſage man, ſhall be appointed Preſident, who may have the overſight of that bounds, and be anſwerable therefore to the Biſhop his Councell and Sy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nod, and he to be reſpected reaſonably for his paines at the modification of ſty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pends, that all things may be orderly done in the Church, peace and quietneſſe maintained in the realm, and we delivered from the appearing plagues, and the bleſſing of God continued, to the comfort of our poſterity.</p>
            <p>And in the mean time, His highneſſe inhibits and expreſly commands under the paines contained in <hi>His Majeſties</hi> Acts of Parliament, and all other pains arbitrall at His <hi>Majeſties</hi> ſight and counſell: That no <hi>Miniſter</hi> take in hand to convene themſelves for the foreſaid cauſe, without the appointment and order taken by the ſaid Biſhops or Commiſſioners, whereby His Highneſſe may be certainly enformed, that the foreſaid <hi>Miniſters</hi> convene not, to meddle with any civill matters, or affairs of Eſtate, as was occaſioned before, but onely to profit in the knowledge of the Word, and to be comforted one by another in the adminiſtration of their ſpirituall Office, which His highneſſe wiſheth them faithfully to diſcharge; and then to call to God that <hi>His Majeſty</hi> may in a pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſperous reign enjoy good and long life, and continue and increaſe into the fear of the Almighty.</p>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The Kings Majeſties intentions.</head>
               <p>HIs Majeſties intention is, by the grace of God, to maintain the true and ſincere profeſſion of the Goſpell and preaching thereof, within this Realm.</p>
               <p n="2">
                  <hi>2</hi> His Majeſties intention is, to correct and puniſh ſuch as ſeditiouſly abuſe the chair of truth, and factionſly apply or other wiſe bewray the text of the Scripture to the diſquieting of the Eſtate, and diſturbing of the Commonwealth, or empairing His highneſſe or Councels honour.</p>
               <p n="3">
                  <hi>3</hi> His Majeſties intention is, if any queſtion of faith or doctrine ariſe, to convo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate the moſt learned, godly, wiſe and experimented Paſtors, that by conference of Scriptures the verity may be tried, and hereſie and ſchiſm by that means repreſſed.</p>
               <pb n="10" facs="tcp:115004:7"/>
               <p n="4">
                  <hi>4</hi> His Majeſties intention is, that for keeping good order in every Pariſh, cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain to be cenſors of manners of the reſt, be appointed at the viſitation of the Biſhop, or Viſitor, who ſhall have His Majeſties authority and Officers of Armes con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curring for the puniſhment of vice.</p>
               <p n="5">
                  <hi>5</hi> His Majeſties intention is, to maintain the exerciſe of propheſie for the encreaſe and continuing of knowledge in the Miniſtery, in the which a wiſe and grave man ſelected by the Biſhop or Commiſſioner at the Synodall aſſembly ſhall preſide; and render an account of the adminiſtration of that bounds where the exerciſe is holden, For which cauſe ſome reſpect of living ſhalbe had to him who ſuſtaineth the burden.</p>
               <p n="6">
                  <hi>6</hi> His Majeſties intention is, not to derogate unto the ordinary judgment of matters of the Church by the ordinary Biſhops, their Councels and Synodes, but if any of them do amiſſe and abuſe their callings, to take order for the correcting, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mending and puniſhing thereof.</p>
               <p n="7">
                  <hi>7</hi> His Maj. intention is, not to hinder or ſtay any godly or ſolid order grounded upon the word of God, and order of the primitive Church, but that the Miniſters of the word, meddle only with their own calling, &amp; judg not temerariouſly of the ſtate.</p>
               <p n="8">
                  <hi>8</hi> It is His Maj. intention, that the Preſbyteries conſiſting of many Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters and Gentlemen at Landwart, or otherwiſe, be no further tolerated within this Realm, but the exerciſe and jurisdictions of the Churches to be in the hands of the Biſhop or Commiſſioner, and their Councels or Synods.</p>
               <p n="9">
                  <hi>9.</hi> His Maj. intention is, that the Biſhops or Commiſſioners convene not any gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall aſſembly out of the whole realm, without His Maj. knowledge, and licenſe ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained thereunto, which upon ſupplication His highneſſe will not deny, that an uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form order may be conſerved in the whole realm, the Biſhops &amp; their diligences there tryed and examined, and the complaints of every particular heard and diſcuſſed.</p>
               <p n="10">
                  <hi>10</hi> It is His Majeſties intention, to aſſiſt this aſſembly himſelf, or by a Noble<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man of his Councell his Deputy.</p>
               <p n="11">
                  <hi>11</hi> It is his Maj. intention, that when any pariſh findeth neceſſity of a Faſt, they intimate the occaſion to the Biſhop or Commiſſioner their Councell, that they may underſtand that the cauſe is lawfull: Likewiſe the Biſhop of the Dioceſſe finding lawfull occaſion, may with his Councell, preſcribe a publike humiliation there.</p>
               <p n="12">
                  <hi>12</hi> It is his Majeſties intention, that a generall Faſt throughout the whole realm, ſhall not be proclaimed but by His Majeſties commandement, or by that generall Councell, wherein His Majeſty or His highneſſe Deputy be preſent.</p>
               <p n="13">
                  <hi>13</hi> It is His highneſſe intention, that the Biſhops in the Realm in every Dioceſſe, with their Councell, preſide into the Eccleſiaſticall government, but as is ſaid, with a Councell, that both tyranny and confuſion may be avoided in the Church.</p>
               <p n="14">
                  <hi>14</hi> It is His highneſſe intention, that Commiſſioners be directed univerſally throughout the whole realm to eſtabliſh a godly order, and that his Majeſties Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſioners take order preſently for the tranſlation of ſuch Miniſters, whoſe travels they eſteem may more conveniently and profitably ſerve in another place.</p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS,</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
